<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Monodia</title>
            <author>Sylvester, Josuah, 1563-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1594</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13276</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23579</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111303</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846674</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846674</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11659</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13276)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11659)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1190:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Monodia</title>
                  <author>Sylvester, Josuah, 1563-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by Peter short,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1594]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: Ios. Siluester.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Caption title reads: Monodia. An elegie, in commemoration of the vertuous life, and godlie death of the right worshipfull &amp; most religious lady, Dame Hellen Branch widdowe, (late wife to the right worshipfull Sir Iohn Branch knight, sometimes L. Mayor of this honorable Citty, and daughter of M. W. Nicholson sometimes of London draper) who deceased the 10. of Aprill last, and lieth interred in Saint Mary Abchurch in London, the 29. of the same, 1594.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of a photostat of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Branch, Hellen, --  Lady, d. 1594 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11659:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11659:1"/>
            <p>MONODIA.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted by <hi>Peter ſhort.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="elegy">
            <pb facs="tcp:11659:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11659:2"/>
            <head>MONODIA.</head>
            <head type="sub">An Elegie, in commemoration of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertuous life, and Godlie Death of the</hi> right Worſhipfull &amp; moſt religious Lady, Dame Hellen Branch <hi>Widdowe,</hi> (<hi>late Wife to the right</hi> worſhipfull Sir <hi>Iohn Branch</hi> knight, ſometimes L. Mayor of this Honorable Citty, and daughter of M. <hi>W. Nichol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſometimes of London Draper) who deceaſed the 10. of <hi>Aprill</hi> laſt, and lieth interred in Saint <hi>Mary Abchurch</hi> in London, the 29. of the ſame, 1594.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ith vnto me vnworthy, you commit</l>
               <l>This worthy taske (for better muſes fit)</l>
               <l>To ſing (nay rather ſadlie to deplore)</l>
               <l>This common loſſe, that nothing can reſtore:</l>
               <l>You ſacred brood, borne of celeſtiall race,</l>
               <l>You virgin Ladies which powre down the grace</l>
               <l>Of Arts and learning on your ſeruants decre,</l>
               <l>Vouch ſafe aſſiſtance to my moornings heer.</l>
               <l>Teach me ſad accents &amp; a weeping meaſure</l>
               <l>To ſtraine foorth pittie, not to ſtir-vp pleaſure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And you my priuate cares, (althogh the cauſe</l>
               <l>Of your diſpaires doo neuer, neuer pawſe)</l>
               <l>Pawſe you a little, and giue leaue a-while,</l>
               <l>Mid publike griefs my priuate to beguile;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11659:3"/>
               <l> Giue leaue I pray you; for a priuate caſe</l>
               <l>Vnto a publike euer muſt giue place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas how fitlie is this life of ours</l>
               <l>Compard to field-graſſe and to fading flowers,</l>
               <l>Freſh, greene and gallant, in the morning ſun;</l>
               <l>Witherd and dead before the day be done.</l>
               <l>Did euer yet the worlds bright eie behold,</l>
               <l>(Since firſt th'Eternal, earthly ſlime en-ſowld)</l>
               <l>A frame of fleſh ſo glorious heer beneath,</l>
               <l>But hath bin ruynde by the rage of Death?</l>
               <l>Of Death dread victor of al earthlie things,</l>
               <l>Who in a moment equals clownes with kings.</l>
               <l>For maieſtie can nothing him diſmay,</l>
               <l>No ſtrength nor courage can his comming ſtay,</l>
               <l>No welth can wage him, nor no wit preuent him,</l>
               <l>No louelie beautie can at al relent him,</l>
               <l>Nay (which is more) no vertue can auaile</l>
               <l>Ay me, that death on vertue ſhould preuaile.</l>
               <l>But tis decreed, death is the meed for ſinne,</l>
               <l>This by ambition did our grand ſire win;</l>
               <l>And we the heires both of his worke and wages</l>
               <l>Muſt all die once, throughout all after ages.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And heere for inſtance ſee this ſable hearſe</l>
               <l>Shrowding the ſubiect of my moornefull verſe,</l>
               <l>The breathleſſe body of a worthie Dame,</l>
               <l>The Lady <hi>Branch,</hi> a <hi>Nicholſon</hi> by name:</l>
               <l>A godlie, vertuous and religious Matron</l>
               <l>For maids, and wiues, and widdows al a pattern.</l>
               <l>Worſhip and wealth adornd hir parentage,</l>
               <l>Fauour and beautie graſt her perſonage,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11659:3"/>
               <l> But vertuous manners, by good education,</l>
               <l>Broght to hir youth the greateſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mendation,</l>
               <l>Wherein ſo wel ſhe ſpent hir virgin-daies</l>
               <l>That Enuies ſelfe ſaw nothing to diſpraiſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now when her age had made hir apt to mary,</l>
               <l>With frends aduiſe that of hir choice were chary,</l>
               <l>She was eſpouſd to one of ſpeciall ſort,</l>
               <l>Welthy in purſe, and worſhip full in port,</l>
               <l>Maiſter <hi>John Minors,</hi> praiſde for zeale &amp; pietie,</l>
               <l>One of the Drapers worſhipfull ſocietie:</l>
               <l>To him ſhe bare fower children, one a boy,</l>
               <l>The reſt al daughters, al, their parents ioy.</l>
               <l>But all theſe ioyes (alas) but little laſted,</l>
               <l>Al theſe faire bloſſoms were vntimely blaſted.</l>
               <l>All dyed young; for what drawes liuely breath</l>
               <l>But yong or ould muſt yeeld at laſt to death?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But they, long moorning for their mutual loſſe,</l>
               <l>Frame mutuall comforts to each others croſſe,</l>
               <l>Till time, that all things weares had worne away</l>
               <l>Their ſorrowes edge, vneaſy to allay.</l>
               <l>Then happilie many fair daies they ſpent,</l>
               <l>To others comfort and their owne content,</l>
               <l>In all the practize of a chriſtian life,</l>
               <l>And mutuall duties meet for man and wife,</l>
               <l>Hee happie in his chance, ſhee in hir choice,</l>
               <l>Both iointly bleſſed in them ſelues reioce.</l>
               <l>But ah theſe earth-ioies doo not euer laſt.</l>
               <l>After long cleerenes cloudes will ouer caſt:</l>
               <l>After long calmes ſtill followes ſtormy weather.</l>
               <l>When they had liu'd full fortie yeares together,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11659:4"/>
               <l> Hee died alas; for what drawes liuely breath,</l>
               <l>But young or ould, muſt yeld at laſt to death?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then deſolate and comfortleſſe alone,</l>
               <l>Like to the Turtle when hir mate is gone,</l>
               <l>With ſigh-ſwolne hart and ſorrow-clowded eies:</l>
               <l>Shee wayles hir loſt loue in a woefull wiſe</l>
               <l>Till time that althinges weares, had worne away</l>
               <l>Hir ſorrowe's edge, vn-eaſie to allay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then after modeſt and meet intermiſion,</l>
               <l>Becomming well hir yeares, and hir codition,</l>
               <l>In ſecond wedlocke ſhee was linckt again</l>
               <l>Vnto another wealthie Cittizen,</l>
               <l>To Maiſter <hi>Branch</hi> who after wards became</l>
               <l>Lord Mayor of London, worthie wel the ſame,</l>
               <l>In which high office he him ſo acquighted,</l>
               <l>That for his ſeruice he was after knighted.</l>
               <l>He was hir husband twentie yeares, or more,</l>
               <l>And much increaſt hir ſtile, her ſtate, and ſtore.</l>
               <l>But boughes &amp; Branches, ſhrubs, &amp; Cedars tall</l>
               <l>Wither and die and into aſhes fall,</l>
               <l>So fel this <hi>Branch,</hi> for what drawes liuely breth</l>
               <l>But old or yong muſt yeeld at laſt to death?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then all forlorne, thus hauing loſt hir knight,</l>
               <l>This doleful Lady left al worlds delight,</l>
               <l>Al ſhewes of pleaſure, and al pomp for ſaking,</l>
               <l>Hir ſelfe to ſadneſſe and to ſoleneſſe taking,</l>
               <l>with inward ſighes &amp; outward teares lamenting</l>
               <l>His death, whoſe life was al hir liues contenting.</l>
               <l>Euen like vnto the ſad and woful Winter,</l>
               <l>Who (ſoone as euer the bright ſeaſon-ſtinter</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11659:4"/>
               <l> Hath left hir widdow of his wonted raies,</l>
               <l>Whilſt to another world he takes his waies)</l>
               <l>Caſting aſide hir rich enameld crownes,</l>
               <l>Flower-powdred ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tles, &amp; embrodered gowns</l>
               <l>Of graſ-green ſilk-ſhag, and the gawdie pride</l>
               <l>Of all hir Iewels and hir iems beſide,</l>
               <l>Hir mirth-leſſe ſelfe in moornfull maner ſhrouds</l>
               <l>Down to the ground in robe of ſable clouds,</l>
               <l>And fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hir ſwoln-hart ſighs a thouſand ſtowres</l>
               <l>And from hir drownd eies weeps a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſhowers.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now become hir ſelf, hir ſelfes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mander,</l>
               <l>To ſhield hir life ſafe from al ſhot of ſlander,</l>
               <l>(As 'twere) ſequeſtred from much conuerſation,</l>
               <l>She paſt hir time in holy meditation,</l>
               <l>In thanks and praier vnto Chriſt our Lord,</l>
               <l>And often hearing of his ſacred word;</l>
               <l>Jn godlie almes, and liberal penſions rife,</l>
               <l>And al the duties of a chriſtian life,</l>
               <l>Laying vp treaſure with the ioyfull iuſt,</l>
               <l>Safe from the force of the eues, and fret of ruſt.</l>
               <l>So that hir three-fold godly life alludeth</l>
               <l>To virgin <hi>Ruth,</hi> wife <hi>Sara,</hi> widdow <hi>Judith,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This life ſhe led; but this life wil away,</l>
               <l>We are but pilgrims, heere we may not ſtay.</l>
               <l>No more might ſhe: for when thrice thirty yeere</l>
               <l>(A goodlie age) ſhe had expired heere</l>
               <l>She alſo died; for what drawes liuely breath,</l>
               <l>But young or old muſt yeeld at laſt to death?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Such life, ſuch death: wel ends the wel begun,</l>
               <l>And by the euen the faire daies praiſe is wun.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:11659:5"/>
               <l> Wel ſhe began and wundrous wel ſhe ended,</l>
               <l>Faire roſe this ſun, and fairely it deſcended,</l>
               <l>To riſe againe to glorie at the laſt,</l>
               <l>At that great angels al-awaking blaſt</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And therfore (deer friends) do not waile nor weep,</l>
               <l>For hir that is ſo happy falne aſleepe,</l>
               <l>But waile our loſſe, our common cauſe of griefe,</l>
               <l>The riches load-ſtar, &amp; the poores releefe,</l>
               <l>For to the rich in life ſhe gaue example,</l>
               <l>And to the poore in life and death was ample.</l>
               <l>Weep rich, weep poore, let high and low lament</l>
               <l>But moſt you poore, let your ſalt tears be ſpent,</l>
               <l>For you alas haue loſt your liberall Ladie,</l>
               <l>Your nurſe, your mother, but alas why wade I</l>
               <l>With my poor ſtile in ſo profound a ſtreame?</l>
               <l>You ſprings of artes, eies of this noble Realme,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Cambridge &amp; Oxford,</hi> lend your learned teares,</l>
               <l>To wail your own loſſe, and to witneſſe theirs:</l>
               <l>Tel you, that haue the voice of eloquence,</l>
               <l>This bounteous Ladies large benificence,</l>
               <l>Firſt to your ſelues, for loue vnto your lore,</l>
               <l>Then ſeueralie to euerie kind of poore,</l>
               <l>Within this Cittie. To the Drapers Hall,</l>
               <l>To euerie Priſon, euerie Hoſpitall,</l>
               <l>To Lunatikes, and poore Maides marriages,</l>
               <l>And many other worthie leagacies,</l>
               <l>And when you haue drawn all your tear-ſprings drie;</l>
               <l>For her deceaſe, heer let your comfort lie,</l>
               <l>That of this Phaenix aſhes there reuiues</l>
               <l>Another, where her vertue ſtill ſuruiues.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Ioſ. Silueſter.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:11659:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
